<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
          <!ENTITY rest "<varname>&amp;rest</varname>">
          <!ENTITY key "<varname>&amp;key</varname>">
          <!ENTITY optional "<varname>&amp;optional</varname>">
          <!ENTITY body "<varname>&amp;body</varname>">
          <!ENTITY aux "<varname>&amp;aux</varname>">
          <!ENTITY allow-other-keys "<varname>&amp;allow-other-keys</varname>">
          <!ENTITY CCL "<literal>CCL</literal>">
          ]>

<chapter><title>The &CCL; IDE</title>
  
  <sect1><title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>Clozure CL ships with the source code for a simple Cocoa
      integrated development environment that runs on Mac OS X. This
      chapter describes how to build and use that environment,
      referred to hereafter simply as "the IDE".</para>

    <para>The IDE is still in a preliminary state, and may lack many
    features you would expect to find in a polished Cocoa
    application. It does, however, provide a text editor and listener
    windows, an inspector for Lisp data structures, and a means of
    easily building a Cocoa application in Lisp. In addition, its
    source code provides an example of a fairly complex Cocoa
    application written in Lisp.</para>

    <para>A more rudimentary version of the Clozure CL IDE has been
      included for several years with the distribution. The current
      version of the IDE has seen the addition of numerous features
      and many bugfixes. Although it's by no means a finished product,
      we hope it will prove more useful than previous versions, and we
      plan additional work on the IDE for future releases.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1><title>Building the IDE</title>
    
    <para>Building the Clozure CL IDE is now a very simple
    process.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In a shell session, cd to the ccl directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run ccl from the shell. The easiest way to do this is
        generally to execute the openmcl or openmcl64 command.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Evaluate the form <code language="lisp">(require :cocoa-application)</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Clozure CL compiles and loads the various subsystems that
      make up the IDE, then constructs a Cocoa application bundle
      named "Clozure CL.app" and saves the Lisp image into
      it. Normally &CCL; creates the application bundle in the root
      directory of the &CCL; distribution.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1><title>Running the IDE</title>
    
    <para>After it has been built, you can run the "Clozure CL.app"
      application normally, by double-clicking its icon.</para>
  </sect1>



</chapter>
